Guide to the Wallace Kaufman Papers, 1959-1994
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Wallace Kaufman papers 1959-1994
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Kaufman, Wallace
1.5 linear feet Extent: 700 Items
Author, teacher, naturalist, environmental activist, and World Bank consultant Wallace Vickers Kaufman was a 1961 graduate of Duke University's Trinity College majoring in English. Collection contains correspondene, reports, journals, and miscellaneous material relating primarily to Kaufman's environmental activism and as a real estate and entrepeneurial consultat. The collection also contains material documenting his friendship with Reynolds Price, a former instructor of Kaufman's at Duke, specifically correspondence, manuscripts, and several typescripts of Price's work.
kaufmanwallace
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is restricted.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Wallace Kaufman Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as gift in 1993-94 and as a purchase in 2008.
Biographical Note
Wallace Vickers Kaufman was born April 10th, 1939 in Queens, New York. Kaufman came to Duke University to study English in 1957, taking his A.B. in 1961. He also studied at Merton College at Oxford University as a Marshall Scholar from 1961-1963.
Along with fellow classmates and writers Fred Chappel and Anne Tyler, Kaufman's writing was fosterd under the direction of William Blackburn. Also while at Duke Kaufman developed a close student-mentor relationship with author Reynolds Price. Kaufman and Price continued to correspond well into Kaufman's own professional career. After graduating, Kaufman taught high school sciences courses, middle school English, and writing courses at Duke University and the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill. While a resident of Chatham County, Kaufman developed an interest in land development projects that included caveats for environmental protection. An extension of this interest led to involvment with, among otehr regional and national environmental organizations, the Conservation Council of North Carolina (CCNC), an organization that Kaufman eventually chaired. Kaufman also served on several local and state boards of realtors, the North Carolina Land Stewardship Council, and Conservation Fund, North Carolina. At this time, Kaufman also travelled extensively in Latin America. During his travels Kaufman promoted indigenous writers, particularly Guatemalan writer Victor Dinoicio Montejo.
In the mid-1990s Kaufman began consulting work for the World Bank and the International City/County Management Association in nations of the former Soviet Union and Eastern Bloc, including Czechoslovakia, Hungary, Poland and Kazakhstan, the final Soviet Republic to declare independence. This work encompassed a broad scope of work including advising local residents on land and housing reform, teaching property valuation, investigating the effectiveness of aid projects, economic surveys, and some work training local journalists. In 2001 Kaufman relocated to western Oregon where he began a career in arbitration and mediation.
Collection Overview
The collection contains correspondence, writings and addresses, journals, reports, clippings and assorted print matter. Materials present primarily reflect Kaufman's environmental activism while residing in rural Chatham County, North Carolina and his consulting work with the World Bank and the International City/County Management Association in the former Soviet Union and Eastern Bloc. Correspondence mostly documents Kaufman's role with the Conservation Council of North Carolina and the organization's collaboration with other local, regional, and national environmental organizations.
The journals and reports document Kaufman's work in former Soviet nations. They describe Kaufman's day to day activities in Hungary, Czechoslovakia, Kazakhstan, and Poland that include descriptions of local customs and geographic regions, the difficulties and challenges inherent in transition from collectivism to privatization, and surveys of local businesses and manufactories. Also present in the collection is material documenting Kaufman's relationship with author Reynolds Price. This material includes mostly correspondence as well as several manuscripts and typescripts. The correspondence touches upon personal matters as well as professional including the activities of mutual friends and acquaintances, travels, and current works in progress.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Kaufman, Wallace; Andrews, Ike Franklin, 1925-; Blackburn, William (William Maxwell), 1899-1972; Esteban, Victor Dinoicio Montejo, 1951-; Preyer, Richardson; Price, Reynolds, 1933-2011; Communist Workers Party (U.S.); Conservation Council of North Carolina; Duke University. Dept. of English; International City/County Management Association; Ku Klux Klan (1915- )--North Carolina; University of Oxford; World Bank. Country Dept. for Czech Republic, Hungary, Moldova, Slovak Republic and Slovenia; World Bank. Country Office in Kazakhstan; World Bank. Europe and Central Asia Region; World Bank; Authors, Guatemalan; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Correspondence; Authors, American -- Southern States; Conservation of natural resources -- North Carolina; Elections -- North Carolina; Environmentalism -- North Carolina; Fascism -- United States.; Literature -- History and criticism; Guatemala -- Foreign relations -- United States; North Carolina -- Politics and government -- 1951-; United States -- Foreign relations -- Guatemala
Related Material
Reynolds Price Papers, 1927-2010 and undated, bulk 1956-2006
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Contents of Collection
- Wallace Kaufman Papers, (3 boxes)
  - Correspondence, 1964-1983 (8 folders) (Box 1)
  - Campaign Material, N.C. House, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Clippings, 1971-1980 and undated (Box 1)
  - Conservation Council of North Carolina (CCNC)
    - Constitution and By-laws, undated (Box 1)
    - Board Meeting minutes, circa 1970s (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, circa 1970s (Box 1)
    - Press releases, 1972-1976 and undated (Box 1)
    - Questionaires, 1972 (Box 1)
    - Resolutions, 1971-1972 (Box 1)
    - Posters, circa 1970s (Box 1)
  - Other environmental organizations, 1970-1980 and undated (Box 1)
  - Montejo, Victor Dionicio, 1984 and undated (Box 2)
  - Photographs (Box 2)
  - Print Material (Box 2)
  - Skidway Institute of Oceanography, Eroding Shorelines, 1981 and 1985 (Box 2)
  - Water Resources and Land Use Task Force, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Writings and Addresses (Box 2)
  - International City/County Management Association and World Bank
    - Hungarian Journal, September 1991 (Box 2)
    - Czechoslovakia Journal, World Bank survey (Box 2)
    - Eastern European Entrepeneurs (Box 2)
    - Alma Alta, Kazakhstan journal, August-July 1993 (Box 2)
    - Kazakhstan journal, July 1993-July 1994 (4 folders) (Box 2)
    - Kazakhstan Real Estate Report, 1993 (Box 3)
    - Poland journal, April-May 1991 (Box 3)
  - Reynolds Price Materials
    - Correspondence, 1959-1989 and undated (8 folders) (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous manuscripts (Price and Kaufman), 1960 and undated (Box 3)
    - Typescripts by Price
      - Troubled Sleep and Michale Egerton, undated (Box 3)
      - A Chain of Love, undated (Box 3)
      - Sleepwalking and The Anniversary 1963 and undated (Box 3)
      - Uncle Grant, undated (Box 3)
      - Morning Places, undated (Box 3)
      - The Names and Faces of Heroes, undated (Box 3)
      - Love and Work, undated (Box 3)
    - Envelopes (Box 3)